Van Pelt found some coded files
in Bertram's office.
It looks like a list.
- Patrick.
- Kim.
"Thank you for this.
I needed the company."
"Who doesn't?"
I'm here to make you an offer.
The bureau is willing to drop
all the charges against you...
- if you come and work for us.
- For the FBI?
My terms. I need you to read 'em
and sign it.
We can work with this.
I'm gonna give you
my home phone number
in case you ever make it
back to the States.
You are on U.S. soil now,
I am the federal government
and I am telling you that this...
is the deal.
That is a napkin.
- Take it or leave it.
- I'll leave it.
- Kim?
- Agent Fischer.
Agent Fischer.
- Have you seen the stapler?
- It busted yesterday.
- We have another one?
- Um...
You know, maybe try
the copying machine.
- It has a staple function.
- Isn't that a waste of paper?
No, we have tons of paper.
I'm gonna go with a paper clip.
- Agent Fischer.
- Chief Lisbon. Can we talk?
It's adorable.
Please. Sit down.
- How's Jane?
- He is still in detention.
I know.
They won't deliver my letters.
Three months now.
He's being kept in isolation by design.
By design?
You mean until he does
what you want.
- We want to help him out.
- You wanna use him.
Is that so bad?
In case you haven't noticed
Jane is hardly federal agent material.
Was he state agent material?
No, not really,
but he wanted to be there.
And while he was there
he stopped the 10-year reign
of a mass murderer
and exposed a society of corruption
in law enforcement
that spread halfway
across the country.
Yeah, that didn't exactly
go down by the books, did it?
Yeah, we know how Jane works.
And we know he's a risk.
But we can't ignore the upside.
He closed every case
you were ever assigned.
- Yeah, he had help.
- Which is why I'm here.
What do you want from me?
Help me, Lisbon.
There are national security
issues at play.
Jane won't work with us
unless we meet his demands.
He has too much pride
to back down.
You gotta give him a win.
Meet one of his demands.
- One of his demands is you.
- Meet another one.
We're running out of time.
Is your work here so pressing
that you can't take a break
to help your country?
Hey, chief, uh,
I radioed Officer Phelps.
He can run to Kmart
for a new stapler.
Swingline or Stanley Bostitch?
Visitor. Splendid.
Not a willing one,
based on the posture.
That's a little better.
It's good to see you.
- How you holding up?
- Ah...
You know
what incarceration's like.
Not really.
Well, there's no need
to pretend, Lisbon.
We're both
in the same predicament.
How is that? I have a home
and a respected career.
You're locked up for murder.
Eh, you're splitting hairs.
We're both trapped.
How am I trapped?
You live in Washington.
- I love Washington.
- High voice.
Why are you being
so stubborn?
The FBI is offering you
a "get out of jail free" card.
Well, you make that sound
like a good thing.
- Isn't it?
- Not on their terms.
If I can't live on my terms
I'm in prison anyway.
Might as well just stay
in this cozy little detention suite.
Well, that's your call,
but not today.
The FBI dragged me here
and they're not gonna let me go home
until you help them with a case.
So get your ass out of the chair
and let's go.
Okay...
Federal officers, coming through.
Thank you.
I don't see a couch anywhere.
Don't start trouble.
At least not yet.
"Security of our national banking system."
"We'll be assisting our
New York office on this case."
And our asset has just arrived.
Mr. Jane. Lisbon.
You called me an asset.
That's so touching.
I'm an optimist.
We just started briefing,
if you'll have a seat.
- I'm fine. Hey, Cho.
- Hey, Jane.
What's going on?
- Hey.
- We're in the middle of a briefing.
- We can catch up later.
- Gotcha. Hey there.
This is Abel Schneiderman.
He led the team
that wrote the new source code
to protect the federal reserve
banking system.
Two days ago, he disappeared
from his loft in Brooklyn.
There were signs of a struggle
in his bedroom.
Schneiderman's cell phone
was busted on the floor.
We are working on the theory
that he has been kidnapped.
- Has there been a ransom demand?
- Not yet, but we're expecting it.
Well, it's either that, or they will
break him for the code
and launch an attack on the
Federal Reserve computer system.
What Abel knows could bring
our banking system to its knees.
Oh. This is exciting.
Is this the case that I'm here for?
- We're getting to you.
- I knew you saw me. Huh?
I knew it.
Abel has a young wife...
Defiance Schneiderman.
Now understandably, she's emotional
and believes that the FBI
is not utilizing
all of its resources
to find her husband.
And unfortunately, we can't let
anyone outside the FBI know
that Mr. Schneiderman's
been kidnapped.
Otherwise, it could cripple
the financial systems.
The New York office sent a FBI agent
posing as a psychic
but Ms. Schneiderman
saw right through that.
Well, of course.
She's a Gypsy.
Woman knows a thing or two
about psychics.
- What makes you say Gypsy?
- Well, Defiance is a Gypsy name.
Look at her bedroom.
It's Gypsy catnip.
Abel there is Jewish,
which means she turned her back
on her entire clan to get married.
Now she has a missing husband
and no family for support.
It's a psychic 911.
Well... there we are.
Let's go to work.
Thank you.
Coach. I was expecting a federal jet
or at least a helicopter.
Call the aisle seat.
You'll sit where you're told.
You know, you can relax.
Everything's good.
You're still a federal detainee
and you're in my charge
so, no, I won't relax.
And you'll do as I tell you,
you understand?
Oh, I understand you, Kim.
I understand you very well...
better than you do yourself.
You will stay within arm's length
of FBI personnel at all times.
Any foolishness,
and you go back to detention.
She wasn't at all like this
on the island.
- How was she on the island?
- I was undercover.
- You mean you were lying.
- I was using a false persona.
Actually, I don't think so.
I think that was the real you.
I think this federal she-wolf shtick
is in fact, a false persona.
No. This is the real me.
We're boarding.
Remember the rules.
Ahh.
I love the smell of reclaimed meat
and onion water.
Do you have a 20?
Thank you.
Liaison with the New York office
is waiting upstairs.
You two, stay here
and cover the exits.
There are two...
west and south.
Detain anyone who tries
to leave the building.
Hey.
Arm's length, remember?
Yeah. I'm just a little hungry.
I don't care.
- I've already paid.
- Now.
This is where
the Schneidermans live.
It's mostly an abandoned
storage building
but there are some renters
on the top floor.
- No security cameras.
- What kind of renters?
Usual fringe types...
artists, dropouts.
These aren't legal dwellings,
but they got a hell of a view.
In the photos you sent
there were signs of a struggle
in the bedroom?
That's this way.
I'll show you.
Hi.
Mrs. Schneiderman?
Defiance.
You are Romani Gypsy?
What do you know about it?
Carny circuit.
My dad was a showman.
So, Defiance. Yeah.
Quite the painter.
- And who are you?
- Patrick Jane.
I was invited by the FBI
they said you need help.
You're a psychic.
So I'm told.
All right.
Read my palm.
It only works
with a dominant hand.
No. Can't do it.
- I knew you were a fake.
- No, you're not letting me in.
You're anxious
about finding your husband
and you don't wanna be read
by a gorger from the government.
You're feeling scared and alone
and you don't trust strangers.
And I don't blame you.
You can't trust these guys.
- Jane.
- I mean, they mean well
and they'll find your husband
if you let them do their thing.
- Says you.
- Yes, says me.
Why are you asking the FBI
to meet your spiritual needs?
Don't you have a trusted psychic
of your own?
I do. Cleo.
But he's not answering
my phone calls.
Hmm. That is odd.
Can you find him?
Can you find Abel?
Where was the last place
you saw him?
On the roof, night before last.
What were you doing up there?
Sharing a bottle of wine
with my girlfriends.
Abel came up there
with his laptop.
He likes to unwind on the roof.
It's peaceful.
I'd like to take a look
at this roof.
It's the stairs
at the end of the hallway.
Hi.
What are you doing?
Spyhole went dark.
What?
We're with the FBI.
Sir, did you see or hear
anything unusual
In the last couple weeks?
- I already told you people, no.
- We're with a different office.
So many, like roaches.
Nice guy.
His name is Nguyen Hai.
He's a Vietnamese refugee.
He used to run a noodle shop.
Now he owns the building.
He was home the evening
of the disappearance
- but he didn't hear or see anything.
- How do you know that?
I read the case files.
I thought you weren't interested
in the case.
It was a long plane ride.
So if Abel came up here
the night he disappeared
why was the bedroom trashed?
I don't know.
I got home late from the bar.
When I got in, Abel was gone,
and our room was wrecked.
Was he expecting any visitors?
I don't think so.
He would've told me
before I left.
This is your husband's garden.
Yeah. How'd you know?
His energy's here.
He pours his energy
into this garden
because he doesn't like
being a computer programmer.
That's right.
He feels trapped in that world.
Yes.
It's an orderly world
full of rules and numbers.
But it's not Abel's world.
He sees himself
more as a rebel soul.
He really loves that
Che Guevara guy.
Yeah, that's why he rides
a motorcycle.
Grows his own vegetables.
That's why he married you.
- Oh, because I'm a Gypsy?
- Yeah.
Because you had the courage
to walk away
from centuries of tradition for love.
You may not know it,
but you give your husband
the courage to be who he is
on the inside.
Is Abel alive?
Why don't you help me find him?
- I can feel him.
- Where is he?
Just not getting a clear read.
What should I do?
Well...
don't tell them I said this
but you should sneak off
and notify the media right away.
So that this city can pull together
and help find him.
That is your only hope
at saving your husband's life.
- Okay.
- Go.
Where's she going?
She, uh... wants to call the press.
I... I tried to stop her.
Downstairs.
You must really miss
that prison cell.
"I'll try and talk to her."
You have done enough talking.
Hi.
After Jane returned
to the roof
he went down a fire escape
to the south alley.
And that's where the cameras
lose sight of him.
Who was covering
the south exit?
I was. But I didn't have a line
of sight to the alley.
There are no exits there,
so I didn't think...
You misread the situation.
There'll be a note in your file.
Yes, ma'am.
Collins wasn't the only one
to misread the situation.
- You mean me?
- Yeah.
You're correct.
I screwed up, too.
And supervising Agent Abbott
will note that in my file.
Fair enough.
Why don't you and Agent Collins
focus on looking for Jane?
You have an insight there.
Coordinate with Davis
in the New York office.
- Yes, ma'am.
- Thank you.
This is the real you, huh?
Let's keep our eyes
on the prize, shall we?
Abel Schneiderman.
We have narrowed
his kidnapping suspects
- to three extremist groups...
- Excuse me?
Why am I here?
- What do you mean?
- I have no business. Jane's gone.
We'll find him.
Uh, most of you will recognize
these faces.
You're only gonna find him
if he wants to be found
which he doesn't, or he wouldn't
have left in the first place.
Take five.
Tell me something...
Did you help Jane escape?
Why would I do that?
You're h... his friend.
Yes, I am, but I'm also
an officer of the law.
I'm not trying to get you in trouble.
I just...
I need your help.
I was so certain
I had him figured out.
Welcome to my life.
How did you make it work
for so long?
I've thought about that myself.
I mean, after he disappeared.
How I made it work for so long.
And what's the answer?
I have no idea.
Were you two ever involved?
That's a strange question.
Why would you ask me that?
Uh...
No reason. I just... I...
uh, nev... never mind.
What are you doing?
Waiting for you.
To do what?
Notice me.
Who are you?
Jason Wylie. Uh, junior I.T. analyst.
I work in I.T.
Analyzing stuff.
Okay.
What do you want, Jason?
Uh, we were told to focus I.T. support
on the Schneiderman case
but I'm my own man
at lunch, right?
So I stole some satellite time
to hunt for Patrick Jane.
Look what I found.
This was taken 22 minutes ago
from a satellite over Brooklyn.
You think it's really Jane?
It's not a trick?
- That's Jane.
- Notify New York right away.
- Who found this?
- Analyst Wylie.
- On his own time.
- Who is analyst Wylie?
Right there.
Feel free to join us.
You took this initiative
on your own?
Yes, sir.
Well, let's see what you can do
on the primary team.
Stanley, find Wylie a desk
in the bullpen.
Down!
Get down!
Face down on the street!
Thank you.
Congratulations.
You got one over on me.
It's a nice stunt.
You feel better now?
No. You woke me up.
I don't get you.
You hunted down
and killed your enemy.
Why are you making new ones?
Eh, you're right.
Running away was a mistake.
I'm ready to discuss
the job offer now.
There is no offer, not anymore.
Nonsense. Let's talk.
I am taking you back to Texas.
And next week, you'll be indicted
for the murder of Thomas McAllister
among other charges.
Guard.
You cats find the body yet?
What body?
The body hidden on the roof
of Abel Schneiderman's building.
You saw it?
No, but there's a large pile of soil
just by the garden.
Winter is almost upon us
so what is that soil doing there?
That's a rhetorical question.
The soil is there
to make room for Cleo...
Mrs. Schneiderman's psychic.
He went missing
the same time as her husband.
What are you talking about?
Abel found out his wife
was sleeping with her psychic
so he killed him in the bedroom.
But Abel doesn't own a car,
so he cut up the body
into pieces and buried them
in the garden.
Your kidnap victim isn't kidnapped.
He's a killer.
And he's on the run.
You're good.
Thank you.
A good liar.
Eh...
I really hope
this isn't his idea of a joke.
There is that chance.
There's also the chance
that he's right.
If there's one thing
that this job kills inside
It's a sense of trust.
I almost forgot what it feels like.
Hey, let me get some light
over here.
Well, there we go.
Hey.
I can't believe
they gave me a desk.
You can call me The Coyote.
I don't think so.
That's just what they
call me downstairs.
Don't ask me why, though.
They never told me.
Your name's Wylie.
Yeah.
Wile E. Coyote.
Road Runner, the cartoon?
No, it's Irish, I think.
Uh, good morning, Agent Stanley.
Hey...
Do you know the road runner
and the coyote?
Yeah. Sex traffickers in Dallas.
There's a cartoon
about sex trafficking?
Hey, Cho, you got a minute?
Yeah.
Abbott and I went
to Brooklyn last night.
There was a body hidden on the roof.
Jane was right.
- He usually is. You get an ID?
- We're waiting on forensics
but it appears to be
Mrs. Schneiderman's psychic
just like Jane said.
The director wants me
to bring him back on the case.
That's a good call.
He made fools of us.
It won't be the last time.
How do I get him under control?
You don't.
Jane is what he is.
He'll use you to turn every situation
to his advantage.
- So what would you suggest I do?
- Use him to your advantage.
- Found the body?
- Yes.
Cleo Ascencio, New York psychic
astrologer, healer.
Also found a hacksaw
hidden in the planters
same brand as the other tools
in Abel's kit
with traces of the victim's blood.
So Abel killed his wife's lover
and ran away
just... like I said.
Well, it appears so.
Oh. Don't beat yourselves up.
You would've figured it out
eventually.
I said, "appears so."
He just received a ransom note.
A third-class letter sent directly
to Abel Schneiderman's office.
What kinda kidnapper
uses snail mail?
It's smart, really.
Low-tech, old school,
no electronic footprint.
Unidentified kidnappers
want $10 million
deposited into an overseas
account by midnight
or they will sell Schneiderman
to the highest bidder.
Next step would be a cyber-attack
on the Federal Reserve.
- You want me to notify secret service?
- Please do.
This isn't right.
There are no kidnappers.
What am I missing?
Maybe Abel faked
his own kidnapping
to get money
to escape the country.
That's very good, Lisbon.
That is the best theory yet
but it's wrong, too.
I need another look at that loft.
Really?
Back to Brooklyn again?
Yeah.
- Okay.
- Don't worry. I won't escape.
Oh, I'm not worried.
If you walk away this time...
I know. I'll end up spending
the rest of my life in prison.
No. I'll shoot you.
Oh, look, they have Skymall.
Skymall.
Okay, Lisbon, what's the matter?
You.
Was it that comment
I made in the bullpen?
Because I think
it's a really good theory.
I don't care about that.
You ran away again, Jane.
Not from the FBI
you ran away from me.
Yeah, but I ran back.
How was I supposed to know?
I thought you were gone
again forever.
Okay, you're right.
I... I'm sorry, Lisbon.
I... I didn't think about you.
Well, you rarely do.
Well, that's not true.
I made you one of my demands.
I'm... I'm not joining the FBI
unless they make you
a job offer.
That's my point.
What makes you think
I wanna work with you again?
You are difficult and exhausting
and maybe I don't wanna put
the rest of my life on hold
to be your sidekick.
Have you ever even thought
about that?
No... No.
I hadn't considered it.
You think you know
what's good for my life
but you haven't been a part
of my life for two years.
So let's get this case wrapped up
so I can go home.
How dare you think
that I would cheat on Abel!
And with Cleo?
No, I... I wasn't reading you.
I was reading your husband.
You're a catch.
Your husband's a computer nerd
pretending to be a rebel
to try and hang on to you.
Men like that snap
when they feel betrayed.
It's true.
Abel is very jealous
and insecure
and he overcompensates
but you missed one detail.
You're in love.
He's my little lion
and I would never sleep
with another man.
I see that now.
I would like to be alone.
Please leave.
Okay.
Do you still think
Abel killed Cleo?
Oh, I know he did.
Guy's a hothead.
Those swollen biceps
and neck tattoos.
The mere hint of an affair
would set that guy off.
Why was her psychic here
the night Abel disappeared?
Defiance was out
with her friends all night.
There was no reason for him
to be at the loft.
Cleo Ascencio.
It's such a theatrical name.
- You think it's real?
- It is. We ran his fingerprints.
- Let me guess. Clean record?
- Spotless.
What are you suggesting, Lisbon?
Ascencio...
it sounds Cuban.
There's a scam
that they do in Cuba.
Brokers charge large sums of money
to surgically modify fingerprints.
They swap the right fingertips
and the left.
It fools immigration every time.
- How do you know that?
- I'm a police chief.
With a lot of reading time
on my hands.
I did what chief Lisbon suggested
and ran the left-hand fingerprints
for the right
and it worked.
Cleo Ascencio transforms into...
Jose Martinez.
- And who is he?
- A fraud.
A street hustler from Havana.
Made a living picking pockets
until he stole a wallet
from one of Castro's ministers.
Now he's wanted by the P.N.R.
Jose Martinez?
He fled Cuba and set up shop here.
Okay, so he changed
his name.
That doesn't mean
he's a fraud.
You have any idea
why he was in your loft
the night your husband
went missing?
Sure. Uh, Cleo would
drop by sometimes
when he thought he had
an insight I should hear.
Now, if you weren't here, would Abel
let him into the building?
He wouldn't have to.
Cleo had the security code.
He would just buzz himself in.
Well, that explains what he was doing
in your bedroom two nights ago.
- It does?
- Hot reading.
It's the bread and butter
of the spiritual flimflam man.
You gather personal effects
on your subject in advance
and then you present them
as psychic revelations.
Martinez came up to see
if Defiance wanted a reading.
But she was out drinking,
and Abel was on the roof.
So he came up into the house
and he took a little snoop.
When Abel came downstairs
he caught your psychic
in the bedroom
and assumed you were
sleeping with him.
Okay. Fine.
But none of that explains
who took Abel from the building.
No, it doesn't, because I don't think
Abel ever left the building.
If my suspicion is correct
he is still here,
and he is still very much alive.
One of us needs to stay here
with Defiance.
- I'll stay.
- You don't want in on the bust?
Nah, the three of us have done
a lotta busts together. You go.
There's nothing like
a takedown with Jane.
Shucks.
Shall we?
One...
Two...
Three.
- Do you know what time it is?
- See?
Distractible and paranoid by nature.
Can't let anyone pass this door
without knowing who it is.
What the hell is going on
out here?
- Glad you asked.
- There's been a murder.
And you said already.
Schneiderman.
No, he was kidnapped.
Another man's been murdered.
But you know that, right?
I don't know
what you're talking about.
Sure, you do.
You know everything
including where Schneiderman
is right now.
I don't know anything.
He's in your apartment, isn't he?
Probably in the bathroom.
No. You value your privacy.
I'm gonna say...
stashed in a closet.
Watch out, Jane.
Open the door, Nguyen!
Uh, somebody gonna break
the door?
Go ahead.
All right, I'm ready.
- Break right.
- Copy that.
I got him.
Go find Schneiderman.
So tell me, Abel
did you invite Jose Martinez
into your loft the night of his death?
No. I came down from the roof
and he was there
in our bedroom.
And what was he doing?
That's what I wanted to know.
"Hey!"
"Hey! Abel!"
"Uh, this isn't what it looks like."
- "What are you doing?"
- "Uh... nothing. See?"
"Where's Defiance?
Defiance!"
"She's not here.
I let myself in! I should go."
"You're not going anywhere!"
"I'm sorry, okay?
I should go."
"I kinda lost it."
"His foot got caught
in the shag throw."
"His... his head hit
the coffee table."
"It was horrible."
And why didn't you call
the police?
With a dead man on the floor?
What you described
is involuntary manslaughter.
You would've been out
in six months.
Then what?
I work the feds.
My career would've been over.
I would've lost Defiance.
That's when I decided
to hide the body.
"And the squeaky
hallway door made sure"
"you always heard
the Schneidermans."
"That is how you came to see Abel
hauling a body to the roof."
"Who is he?"
"Just somebody
who deserved what he got."
"This...
This is a bad dream."
"Just go back to bed,
Mr. Nguyen."
"I'm not sleepy."
"What do you want?"
"You want money? Fine."
"I'll give you $5,000"
"to forget everything
you saw here tonight."
"You're that security contractor
for the federal government."
"Yeah."
"Exactly how much are you worth
to the government?"
Our colleague Mr. Jane suspected
there was more to you
than meets the eye.
You didn't get those scars on your face
from running a noodle shop.
You're a gangster from way back.
Green Dragons?
"Born To Kill".
It was the bloodiest street gang
in New York history.
All Vietnamese refugees.
I hear you guys owned Chinatown
in the '80s.
We owned New York.
One last story
for the record books.
How an original member of B.T.K.
almost took the feds for 10 million.
Give me that confession.
Give me the pen.
You wanted to talk to me?
You have a sharp mind.
And people like you.
Some people.
Well...
I didn't think so before
but I can see this arrangement
working on a permanent basis.
I like you, too, Dennis.
And I can see working with you
in the future
but only on my terms,
and you know that.
Yeah, we've been through this.
There's no deals.
No demands, no negotiations.
We are offering you a career,
a clean slate.
A chance to make a difference.
You drive a hard bargain, Dennis.
Okay, pet leopard's off the table.
Forget about that.
But I need the full pardon.
And the airstream.
And I need a couch, man
'cause everything is cold
and hard around here.
And...
I need a job offer for Lisbon.
I am sure that some people
find this side of you endearing...
but I'm not one of them.
I'll be following
your murder trial on the TV.
- Good luck.
- Okay.
Thank you.
Oh, enjoy your mail.
Fellas. Stop right there.
Jane...
where did you get this from?
Oh, a thumb drive
Gail Bertram was hiding.
This is the first
I'm hearing about it.
It's the first I've talked of it.
These are all the members
of the Blake Association.
Correct.
I figured Bertram was keeping it
as insurance.
Well, we've arrested or retired
all of these people.
Yes, you have...
Except the ones
that I've blacked out.
Those ones you haven't caught.
- We caught 'em all.
- Did you?
Well, I guess Bertram was wrong then.
Give me the names.
A couple of judges, a congressman
several FBI agents.
- Names.
- Big names, some of them.
If that list ever got out
to the press
it'd cause all kinds of turmoil,
wouldn't it?
- Are you threatening me?
- Oh, no.
Just pointing out that we both have
the power to create misery.
Okay.
You give me the names,
and we'll agree to all of your terms
on the contract.
If I give you the names,
you'll break the contract.
You've already done it once.
What do you propose?
I propose that you surrender
to my terms
and when I'm finished
with your contract
and only then
I will give you the names.
Get him outta here.
Well...
You did it this time.
You brought the FBI to its knees.
- Did I?
- And they conceded to all your demands.
Every single one.
How did you do it?
Well, remember that thumb drive
we found in Bertram's wine cellar?
The encrypted database?
It's a list
of Blake Association members.
- I used it as leverage.
- But we never broke the encryption.
Yeah, the FBI doesn't know that.
That's why you escaped.
To create a bogus list of names.
And to enjoy
a bacon-wrapped hot dog.
I have to say, I am impressed.
- You outplayed the FBI.
- No contest.
Did they tell you
when I start work?
When we start.
We?
- What about your job?
- Nah. It was boring.
- Yeah, I told you.
- Yeah. But you had no right to.
It's my life, and I'll decide
what to do with it.
- And you decided correctly.
- There was never any choice.
Oh, come on. It'll be fun.
Let's see what kinda trouble
we can make.
- I got you something.
- For me?
You got me socks.
Handmade in Washington.
Oh...